Unpolished. Unkempt. Unleashed. Undercover.
Miss Congeniality is a comedy, crime, action film directed by Donald Petrie.
When the local FBI office receives a letter from a terrorist known only as 'The Citizen', it's
quickly determined that he's planning his next act at the Miss America beauty pageant.
Because tough-as-nails Gracie Hart is the only female Agent at the office,
she's chosen to go undercover as the contestant from New Jersey.
Gracie Hart, played by Sandra Bullock.
Eric Matthews, played by Benjamin Bratt.
Cheryl Frasier, played by Heather Burns.
Victor Melling, played by Michael Caine.
Harry McDonald, played by Ernie Hudson.
Kathy Morningside, played by Candice Bergen.
Miss Congeniality is a 2000 American action comedy film directed by Donald Petrie, written by Marc Lawrence, Katie Ford, and Caryn Lucas, and produced by and starring Sandra
Bullock as Gracie Hart, a tomboy agent who is asked by the FBI to go undercover as a contestant when a terrorist threatens to bomb the Miss United States pageant.
Michael Caine, Benjamin Bratt, Candice Bergen, William
Shatner, and Ernie Hudson star in supporting roles.
Miss Congeniality was released in the United States by Warner Bros.
Pictures on December 22, 2000.
It received mixed reviews from critics and grossed $212
million worldwide against its $45 million budget.
The film earned Bullock a nomination for a Golden Globe Award for
Best Actress – Motion Picture Comedy or Musical.
It was followed by the sequel Miss Congeniality 2: Armed and Fabulous in 2005.
The film explores themes of undercover agent, investigation,
beauty contest, talent show, fish out of water.
The tone is lighthearted.